條例草案交由內務委員會處理。
本會現在恢復2014年印花税修訂條例草案嘅二讀辯論，有冇議員想發言？
梁繼昌議員。
多謝主席。
我係commenting on the stamp duty amendment bill two hundred and one four.
香港 remains a competitive economy, mainly due to the fact that we have a low and simple tax regime.
而低和 simple 税制 regime 始終係香港經濟成功嘅 cornerstone，喺過去，亦都係未來。
In addition, it is always important to stay alert to our competitors, what they are doing, what they have done or what they will be doing in future, so that we are not losing our competitive edge.
looking at all the major financial markets.
It has been the practice of major financial markets.
Like U.S., Australia.
日本、韓國，和新加坡。
for not imposing stamp duty on the transactions of exchange traded funds, whether they're in share form or in unit form.
The United Kingdom has also recently removed all stamp duties on ETFs that are domiciled in the UK, and it happened last April.
looking back, Mr. President.
我 have had a privilege of providing my professional service to the first ETF in the city.
The tracker fund back in 1999.
我 remember that that was a very hectic transaction and.
It took place all within a matter of a month and a half.
我 vividly remember that during that period where we did not have this type of stamp duty exemption legislation.
We had to go through a lot.
of procedures in obtaining a stamp duty exemption for the tracker fund.
and I think the government is moving in the right direction.
to extend exemptions to exchange traded fund.
Exchange traded fund is become a fashionable investment instrument mainly because of the fact that.
它可以提供。
一風險 divestment instrument for investors with relatively no or little investment experience.
Against this background, I'm ready to give my support to the current.
proposal of extending the stamp duty concession.
In respect of trading of ETFs to cover ETFs, with the value of Hong Kong stock exceeding 40% of the aggregate value of the underlying portfolio.
In other words， the stamp duty for the transfer， buy and sell， and any transfer involving a change of beneficial interest of all ETF shares or units will be waived.
Although, Mr. President, I believe that the market as a whole.
Will want more concession from the government in relation to the waiving of stamp duty in respect of ETFs.
now looking at how ETFs been doing in
our neighbouring markets.
我記得，在新加坡交易所。
The average daily turnover in Hong Kong dollar terms for ETFs amounts to about 57.2 billion Hong Kong dollars.
and and whereas in Hong Kong, the comparative figure was only about 14.24 billion.
作為立法者，我已經倡議多元化我們的經濟基礎、我們的經濟活動。同樣地，適用於金融工具的多元化。
The more diversified our financial instruments are, the merrier I think the market participants, and the
widen the choice we're given to the investors in our region.
and so I hope with the introduction of the exemption of stamp duty, that could you know speed up the
Introduction of ETFs, more ETFs to be listed on the stock exchange. However, I also do remind Professor Chan that.
granting exemption or giving tax incentives is one thing.
The other thing I think most practitioners or market participants find.
which are barriers to the entrance of the Hong Kong market. Is the time ticking, perhaps for the SFC to approve the the instrument itself?
I'm not saying that we should lower the threshold or we should relax the regulatory regime, but rather I would like the speed and efficiency of the relevant regulator to be speed up.
A conducive tax environment is an important and indispensable factor.
驅動了增長的， not only the ETF market， but also the asset management industry as a whole.
要 keep us competitive against the other global financial centres.
I will also urge the government to continuously explore other tax-friendly initiatives in order to maintain Hong Kong's position as a premium asset management centre in Asia in a timely and effective manner. Thank you, Mr. President.
仲冇其他議員上發言。
我現在向各位提。
陳監林業。
主席。
亞洲區嘅。
經濟增長咧係非常之迅速，再加上內地嘅金融市場日漸開放。
香港作為內地對外嘅一個橋頭堡咧，喺吸引不同類型嘅基金，以香港作為基地。
係具有優勢嘅。實際上喺香港上市嘅交易所嘅買賣嘅基金咧，係持續增加嘅。由二零一零年年底嘅六十九隻大幅增加，至到二零一四年九月三十號嘅一百二十一隻。
而呢一類嘅基金，平均每日嘅成交額咧。
亦都由二零一零年嘅二十四億係持續增加至到二零一三年嘅三十七億元。無論從基金嘅數目以至到成交額，我哋都可以睇到香港嘅交易所買賣嘅基金係不斷嘅增長。不過喺發展嘅同時咧，呢一類嘅基金喺香港仍然面對住。
住一啲嘅掣肘嘅，好似話根據現行嘅法律法例，如果交易所買賣基金喺香港處誒。
被存持有人持有人登記冊而追蹤嘅相關指數裏邊咧，港股所佔嘅比重係高於百分之四十，買賣雙方係需各自付印花税。至於金額則按成交額嘅百分之零點一計算。
相比之下，其他司法管轄區包括澳洲、日本、南韓、中國內地、新加坡同埋美國，都已經係冇徵收呢個印花税㗎啦。
所以，就算喺英國咧，喺舊年嘅四月起咧，亦都同其他地方接軌，係免除當地成立嘅交易所買賣基金嘅印花税。
所以全球嘅金融市場嘅競爭咧，可以講係越嚟越激烈，而香港相對嘅吸引力就不斷嘅減弱。根據政府提供嘅資料。
環顧亞太區十四個交易所嘅交易所買賣嘅基金總成交額咧，香港所佔嘅比重由二零一零年嘅百分之三十係下跌下跌到二零一三年嘅百分之十七左右。
主席，選擇喺咩地方上市基金發行人咧？一般都會考慮多種嘅因素，包括市場嘅情況、業務發展嘅優先次序、成本，以至到法律同埋税務嘅制度。
當然。
當局通過呢一條嘅條例去全面嘅寬免交易所買賣基金嘅印花税呢，肯定係有助於吸引交易所買賣基金以香港作為基地。
以本地基金業嘅產品種類同埋業務嘅範圍，亦都可以因此咧係進一步拓寬嘅。
民建聯係完全支持本條例草案嘅提出，原因咧主要有三個。第一就係通過本條例草案，可以令香港喺税務制度上與其他嘅市場競爭對手看齊。
站喺同一個起點嚟到競爭，其次就係呢一次嘅寬免咧，其實唔係誒首次嘅。喺二零一零年，當局曾經將印花税嘅寬免範圍係擴闊至到涵蓋港股佔相關指數比例不高於百分之四十嘅交易所買賣基金。
自此之後咧，總共有九十二隻新嘅交易所買賣基金喺香港上市。根據呢一個經驗，呢一次再進一步嘅寬免咧。
我哋預期可以鼓勵更多嘅發行人將交易所買賣嘅基金咧嚟到香港上市，提高呢一類基金嘅每日成交額，對市場咧係有利嘅。
對於香港作為國際金融中心嘅發展，亦都係有所裨益嘅。第三點咧，就係當局喺二零一零年將印花税嘅免税額涉及少收嘅政府税項咧，每年大約只係六億係至到八億元。至今次嘅至於今次嘅印花税負。
冠冕咧預料少收嘅嘅税項咧，但係只有一億，所以税款上嘅損失咧根本係唔多嘅。總括嚟講咧，民建聯認為建議係有助提高香港作為國際金融中心嘅競爭力，促進香港喺開發、管理同埋買賣交易所。
買賣基金嘅發展，亦可為所有嘅香港上市交易嘅所誒交易所買賣基金帶嚟公平競爭嘅環境。所以，即使本條例草案令政府嘅税收係稍為減少，民建聯咧都認為係值得嘅。
不過，除咗關心基金發展，民建聯亦都關注到通過本條例草案是否會引發至到一啲所謂市場嘅濫用嘅問題，特別係上市公司會否係為咗逃避繳納印花税税款而將本身嘅股份重新包裝，成為交易。
所買賣基金，我哋都留意到按法規嘅要求，目前交易所買賣基金咧被歸類為集體投資計劃，係必須要按照相關嘅規定係獲得證監會許可嘅。所以我所以我哋咧係促請證監喺通過條例草案。
之後做好喺呢一方面嘅把關工作。
最後就係通過呢一條條例草案咧，係香港發展資產管理嘅一小步。民建聯更加關心當局會否繼續採取一啲咩嘅措施去鞏固香港作為企業財富管理中心嘅地位。除咗政府正在研究吸引企業喺香，
香港成立企財中心嘅措施之外咧，我哋亦都促請政府係考慮進一步擴闊與內地證券金融市場嘅互聯互通，拓展金融高端嘅服務，提高服務增值嘅能力，進一步鞏固人民幣離岸中心同埋資產管理中心嘅地位。
與此同時，我哋亦都促請政府同埋內地之間嘅資產管理業嘅合作，盡快建立兩地基金跨境認可嘅制度。主席，本人跟住陳詞支持條例草案予以議讀。
仲有冇其他嘢想發言？
如果冇嘅，現在我就請財經事務及副務局局長答發言答辯。喺局長答辯後，辯論即告結束。財經事務及副務局局長。
主席，我感謝議員對二零一四年。
印花税修訂條例草案，下稱條例草案嘅支持，令條例草案能夠恢復二讀辯論，以便早日落實二零一四至一五年財政年度政府財政預算案嘅建議，全面豁免交易所買賣基金股份或單位轉讓嘅印花税。
正如我喺熱動耳耳讀嘅時候表示，交易所發牌基金業務係全球資產管理業嘅重要一環，而且增長迅速。
交易所為基金發行人，在決定基金成立地或上市地時，有利嘅税務環境係重要嘅考慮因素之一。
鑑於亞洲嘅金融市場日趨融合，自二零一零年起，我哋把港股佔相關指數比重不高於百分之四十嘅交易所買賣基金納入印花税減免範圍。
在香港上市嘅交易所買賣基金數目，由二零一零年年底嘅六十九大幅增至二零一四年年底嘅一百二十二。
香港亦成為，亦成為咗亞太區最大嘅交易所買賣基買賣市基金市場之一。
不過，就未獲減免嘅印花税嘅交易所買賣基金而言，買賣雙方仍需各自繳付印花税。
在主要嘅國際金融市場中，目前只係有香港營就交易所買賣基金徵收印花税，這不但影響香港作為區內交易所買賣基金輸入嘅地位。
亦影響港股佔相關指數比重高於百分之四十嘅交易所買賣基金嘅競爭力。
政府喺本年。
喺本財政年度嘅政府財政預算案中，建議全面寬免。
交易所買賣基金股份或單位轉讓嘅印花税，令港股佔相關指數比重高於百分之四十嘅交易所買賣基金，同樣可降低交易成本。
這有助促進香港交易所萬眾基金市場嘅發展，並為所有交易所萬眾基金，不論其資產組合，提供合提供公平嘅競爭環境。
轉讓交易所買賣基金嘅股份或單位所需繳付嘅印花税，目前在印花税條例於已定明，條例草案修訂印花税條例，以便全面寬免相關嘅印花税。
全面豁免交易所買賣基金股份或單位轉讓嘅印花税嘅建議，將由印花税修訂條例刊憲當日起生效。換句話講，若本會在這個會議通過條例草案，相關嘅印花税豁免將由本年二月十三日。
一起生效。
主席全面寬免監獄所買賣基金股份或單位轉讓印花税。
有助促進香港交易所買賣基金市場嘅發展，並有助鞏固香港嘅資產管理中心地位，推動金融服務業嘅整體發展。
既為業界帶嚟新嘅商機，又可以為投資者提供更多元化嘅產品。我希望本會能夠通過條例草案。多謝主席。
現在我哋提出嘅代決議題係《二零一四年印花税修訂條例草案》二二讀，咁現在付諸表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。二零一四年印花税修訂條例草案，全體委員會審議階段，本會現在成為全體委員。